hi there this is a Christian Dy with latitude west
financial and i thought it would be prudent to
summarize the changes happening
in september with the manulife
disability plan for dentists and i thought the
absolute best way to do this was to bring in the
manulife representative darrell faulkner and so
daryl is going to tell us uh exactly the changes
that are happening to the manulife uh plan and
um describe a little bit about its consequences
so manulife is canceling and for as long as i have
worked with uh ubc with the dentist they've always
provided the 4a disability plan uh darryl can
you just describe you know the manual for a plan
uh disability insurance for the dentist uh sure
thing christian uh first thanks for having me uh
having me today so for as long as i've been at
manny life which is 13 years manulife has offered
our proguard contract which i
think we can both agree is the
strongest contract in the market and while
other carriers other companies reduce the
occupation class uh down to a 3a occupation
class manulife held firm at a at a 4a so
removing this this product for sale um does have
some some consequences for all our clients but
specifically the the dentist that we're talking
about today um one would be a an increased premium
a 4a occupation class is deemed to be a less
risky less likely to claim occupation class
than a 3a and so the the less risky an occupation
class the less a client would pay for that premium
so by by losing that occupation class
any any policyholders any applicants
applying at any other carriers at a 3a would be
facing an increased cost to uh to buy that product
and own occupation is uh is fairly important
on a 4a plan which manulife has if a client was
to get a product without a 4a sorry if a client
was to get a product without a occupation class
own occupation class essentially what they're
losing is um if they were on a claim then uh for
example if they had um injured themselves so they
couldn't practice dentistry anymore but they were
able to do other um jobs at a lesser cost maybe
teaching or a lab tech or something of that sort
because they're employable and because if they had
no own occupation class on it that would mean that
they can be essentially kicked off of a claim is
that correct correct if the the regular occupation
definition would essentially kick in and
you you use an example that i always use um
when talking about dentists or doctors if
you don't have the ability to practice but
you have the ability to teach for example the own
occupation definition would allow you to receive a
a claim from from manulife or
or any carrier for that matter
since you're not able to practice dentistry but
well well teaching the the regular occupation
uh definition would mean that since you're
able to do something like teach or you know
be employed as a lab tech your your benefit would
would cease to exist got it so having a 4a with an
own occupation class incredibly incredibly
important for a dentist because of course
going from dentistry making you know two three
hundred thousand per year and then all of a sudden
going to something which which it wasn't dentistry
almost guaranteed to take a significant drop
you're you're losing money in terms of salary but
the amount of time that that any any potential
client going through dentistry school has spent
you know getting through undergrad then getting
through uh through ubc dental school or wherever
they're at is a tremendous amount of time and a
tremendous amount of effort and so being able to
protect that with the the own occupation class
in my mind is is hugely important absolutely
and and and i guess a a third uh uh one to
highlight is the lower limits um so so tell
us a little bit about you know uh the limits
the the limits that come with uh uh um for the
dentist when uh uh when they're getting this plan
so we have with with manulife we have a a
i believe a higher starting limit for your
your monthly benefit but also the ability
to purchase additional insurance uh without
medical evidence in the in the future at a higher
occupation class a less risky occupation class
manulife allowed more benefit to be purchased now
that that is that is off the table it could mean
the the option to purchase higher amounts of
insurance in the future as your clients income
increases is is diminished yeah absolutely because
i know it's you know somewhere in the neighborhood
of 20 000 per month of coverage which for their
future insurability so what that means is that
if a dental student was to purchase the absolute
minimum which is around 500 per month of coverage
they have a maximum in first year or
second year or third year that they can
they can purchase of 1500 per month of coverage
but when they get this when they're in fourth year
this up to 3 500 per month of coverage
and then after that they're subject to um
their uh they're subject to whatever their income
will provide so let's say your income shows that
you can get coverage of 12 000 per month of
coverage well with a manulife plan at a 4a
you're able to go to that level without evidence
of medicals that you took back when you were in
first year so now you know you might be in your
mid-30s but you signed up for this when you're 22
so you know uh or 23. so so now there is no more
evidence of medicals because that limit is so high
but when the limit is significantly lower you
might have to redo more medicals you might
have to reapply you might even need to get
a different company to insure you because um
because of a of a 3a policy will always have
a lower limit than a 4a policy so getting this
4a policy you'll never have to do another medical
for your disability insurance for your entire you
know dental career which is why even though you
are quite young and you're thinking i'm not even
working right now it's so incredibly important
to take advantage of this last opportunity to
get manualized for a disability plan so so um you
know go losing this foray you're essentially going
to end up paying more for insurance you could
potentially be losing this bone occupation uh
for sure you're losing your own occupation uh with
the manulife 4a plan and you're going to end up
having more limits as well so uh daryl did you
was there any last thing that you wanted to add
in regards to the changing plan i mean bottom line
i mean obviously i worked for manulife but i've
heard from yourself and other advisors that that
progard is the the best contract on the market for
professional executives so um it is it is a shame
that we're we're losing it and and hopefully you
have you have a chance to sit down with Christian
and get an application before yeah exactly and i
i think the um from my my long long experience
with ubc dentistry all of the clients uh that
i've dealt with always will get a manulife 4a and
the only real reason why not to get a manulife
4a plan is if you don't qualify for it maybe
for some medical reason or things of that sort
uh yeah so i i now want daryl you know to talk
about myself in the elite program with manulife
absolutely absolutely and and so before i do that
um i'll a little bit about myself so my name is
daryl faulkner i'm director of individual
insurance sales for for british columbia um
christian you and i have worked together for just
over 11 years now um great working relationship
uh fantastic advisor has a has a fantastic team
at latitude west um i've heard nothing but but
great things about any of the clients that that
i've interacted with um in dealing with christian
um and and as this slide shows christian is a an
elite producer with with manulife this is a small
and as the name suggests very elite group with
with manulife there are less than 250 total
elite producers across the country of over what i
believe is 15 000 contracted um advisors with with
manulife so so christian is part of a very small
and elite group uh who qualifies for this this
recognition every year um and and i do believe
he's uh he's one of the only elite advisors who
who works with the the dentist at ubc and and so
as great as that is for christian it does mean
great things for for you the client um you know
being being elite gives christian access to our
our top underwriters our our top underwriting team
it gives him and his applications priority access
once they've been received in underwriting once
they've been approved um it gets priority handling
to get to get sent out the door and sent to
christian so he can physically deliver that
deliver that contract all this means a quicker
better experience for for you the end client
and and so for me for for my money um you
know if if i was in a position where i needed
disability insurance i would i would definitely
be speaking with christian and trusting him with
with my policy and i say that one because of his
his expertise um you know the time the dedication
he's put into to learning the practice um building
his building his practice and his craft but also
the relationship that he has with uh with myself
and the the greater manulife team yeah no thank
you so much so i've always prided myself on
working with my clients and making sure that
i get their policies in as fast as possible uh and
helping to navigate if there's any health issues
or any underwriting issues at all i want to make
sure that they are 100 fully fully um informed on
on all of their best options uh whether we should
move forward on the application whether we should
postpone whether we should get additional you
know doctor's notes as well as on the claim side
uh unfortunately because i've been in the business
so long i have had multiple multiple people
make claims on disability on critical illness
online uh and i've never had a claim not issued
um so it for my clients it's always
actually been a very very smooth process so
i can honestly say you're in very very good hands
by putting your trust and faith into myself in um
in getting a manual life plan for your disability
insurance so um thank you so much uh daryl for
uh for for just informing us as to what
is going on as well as informing everyone
about what is the advantage of of using an elite
advisor and and i am the only elite advisor at UBC
dentistry in order you know and if if a ubc dental
student wanted there to be the most quickest and
seamless way of getting this application i
highly recommend you use myself and my team
so you know um uh if you're ready to talk and
figuring out how to move forward we always do
a complimentary call there's no obligation we
could run quotes right away if there was a need
to apply we can do an online application because
i know a lot of the students are quite busy so
if you want to book a call assistant at latitude
dash west.ca but if you even had just a question
directly for me i always give my my clients direct
access to me that's my cell number you could text
message me with a question or give me a call
and then we're happy to give you a hand so once
again darrell uh thank you for helping us out and
understanding thank you for the relationship that
you continue to have with myself in manulife and
i will absolutely continue to be your top advisor
here in BC as i have been since 2017. thank you
very much christian it was happy to be here okay